dr.nader gulping here we're back talking
5-minute physiology today's topic on
physiology of strength one of the
questions I get asked a lot don't like
to ask my students actually is is it
fizzy much big possible to get stronger
without getting bigger in another video
we'll talk about the physiology of
getting bigger or I heard you pee and
how that it improves the strength but
what I want to ask here is once the
physiology of drew strength improvements
independent of science games all right
so I go through some training five weeks
later on stronger I'm not that stupid
bigger I don't have any more muscle mass
how is it physically possible I've
produced more force well we have three
components to consider in fact we have
to just understand how contraction
happens in the first place so if I make
my bicep move in fact I'll grab my
dumbbell that was accidentally right
here and it happens to be 45 pounds I
didn't anticipate that I was going to
curl this but now I'm not going to but
if I could girl this very like that okay
so what happened is my biceps muscles
there that go through the insert on the
front of my arm in the ball so when my
biceps contract they pull my bones
actually makes this weight move okay so
I have one component of something
pulling on my bum a second component of
the muscle contracting the third
component is me telling my muscle to
contract all right so if we go actually
the backwards order there the first
thing we're paying attention to are
our neurological okay so what that means
is it starts with your brain or
somewhere now your your brain stem or
your spinal cord then you have some sort
of neurological activation now folks
often refer that as your C and s and
here lots like the coaches that people
talk about that CNS stands for your
central nervous system again your brain
brain stem and spinal cord so you have
some impulse per meter logical suspect
so one of the adaptations that we know
happen is you simply get better at that
process you activate more motor units
you turn on the proper ones you let go
let go of some that don't need any other
and you learn exactly it makes the right
sequence so you have a bunch of
neurological adaptations the second
thing that can happen
is the actual muscle right so what most
folks don't realize it and not muscle
back so I get muscle all the credit is
that the muscle itself can get stronger
quote-unquote without necessarily
getting any bigger people realize if the
fiber gets bigger it looks stronger but
the contractile properties of the muscle
fiber itself so what I mean is if I take
a muscle biopsy of your bicep and then
we take it into my lab and we pull out
individual muscle fibers and we cook one
end of those muscle fibers up to a force
transducer and tie their either ended up
to the piece of metal the ability of
that muscle to contract with more force
is improved with strength training a
bunch of there were physiological
components to that things like calcium
sensitivity potentially fiber type
transformations among other things my
elated to produce more force without
necessarily being any bigger so we could
be singing there lots of occasions we
could be seeing muscle out of patients
we're probably seeing a combination and
then the third thing we start with
is your connective tissue this is your
fashion right this is that the lining of
each individual muscle fiber so all the
individual fibers in your biceps have
this faster that's around it then a
bunch of those things are put together
and we have fashion around that and then
we've got the entire muscle with fashion
around that and then the factory muscles
all come together to make your tendons
your tendons are what actually attach to
your bone and that's what actually
allowed me to pull that don't belong in
the air so this is probably the
Forgotten child of performance or of all
adaptation this is the fact that we see
improvements and changes at the level of
the connective tissue so this again
would be the connective tissue around
the individual fibers around the whole
entire muscle and how that all comes
together to form a tendon which inserts
onto a bone it's allowed you to actually
go long evolve so again we've got three
different adaptations probably all three
of them are adapting at some level most
folks give them the neurological
component most of the credit especially
early on in strength training
applications will be CDs happening this
is also happening but probably less well
defined certainly a lot less research
and lots a lot less well understood so
that's it that's our physiology of
strength training hopefully that helped
feel free to contact me on Twitter
Instagram Facebook if you have doctor
any Galpin or check out the website and
intercom if you're not there right now
for more videos like this let me know if
you have any questions of your thoughts
and if you like that you know let me
know we wanna see next I'm up for any
topic we'll see you next time on
5-minute physio
you